Léon Hartl Papers
Léon Hartl Papers
1924-1966
Hartl, Léon, 1889-
0.25 linear ft.
Published material, exhibits, newspaper and magazine clippings. biographical material.
2741972
Biographical History
Léon Hartl (1889-1973) was a French-born painter known for his figures, still lifes and landscapes. He emigrated to American in 1912 and spent much of his working life in New York.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Léon Hartl Papers consists of biographical material, correspondence, exhibit material, and printed material.
Biographical material consists of an autobiographical packet compiled by and/or for the Peridot Gallery.
Correspondence includes the National Academy of Arts and Letters, and an unknown "Cher Amie."
Exhibit material contains catalogs and magazine and newspaper clippings relating to exhibits at a variety of galleries.
Printed material has clippings regarding Hartl and his work, from American newspapers and magazines as well as from French and German publications.
Arrangement of the Collection
Folders are alphabetical by topic. Clippings in each folder are in chronological order.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Hartl, Léon, 1889-; Painters -- United States.; Art, Modern.; Clippings (information artifacts); Exhibition catalogs.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Léon Hartl, 1966.
1954 letter to "Cher Amie" purchased, 2013.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Peridot Gallery biographical packet, 1964 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - National Academy of Arts and Letters, 1959; regarding award; includes printed material (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, outgoing, 1954 (Box 1)
    Letter to "Cher Amie" purchased, 2013.
- Exhibits
  - Brummer Gallery, 1934-1938; exhibit brochures, clippings (Box 1)
  - GRD Studio show, 1929; clippings (Box 1)
  - International Studio, 1926; handwritten and typed copy of review (Box 1)
  - Peridot Gallery, 1954-1964; undated; exhibit brochures, clippings (Box 1)
  - Valentine Gallery, 1926; 1936-1940; exhibit brochures, clippings (Box 1)
  - Whitney Studio Club, 1925; exhibit brochures, clippings (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1928; 1956,; 1965-1966 (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Clippings, magazine, 1953; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, newspaper, 1924; 1955,; 1959 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, French press, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, German press, 1927 (Box 1)